Okay, now, all over the world, the Toyota pickup truck is marketed as the toughest vehicle money can buy.
I'm going to show you an advertisement from Australia, and if you've got any children watching,
put your fingers in their ears, because it does contain some Australian language.
Bugger.
Bugger me.
Easy now, son.
Ooh, bugger.
Bugger.
And, and, it's not just ad speak either, because whenever you turn on the news,
what is it that's always bogging down the enormous American military machine?
Yeah, it doesn't matter whether it's Kosovo, Iraq, Afghanistan, wherever,
you've always got a bunch of guys who rock up in their home clothes with a half-timbered machine gun,
and look, all of them in a flatbed Toyota.
So, it's very popular in Australia and all the other various bits of the third world.
But would it work here? Well, we had to find out.
For £1,000, we got a 13-year-old Hilux diesel, which had done 190,000 miles.
And, judging by the state of it, only ten of them had been done on the road.
We love cars like this on Top Gear.
It's why we like the Citroen Berlingo and the Daihatsu Chirag,
they're simple, honest-to-God engineering.
But this gives us a problem.
See, when we get a Porsche to test, we find out how fast it goes,
and we get a Renault Megane, we find out how safe it is.
But this, as you know, is built for strength.
So, we've got to find out how tough it is.
That's why we brought it to Bristol.
This city has an air of solidity about it.
The paving stones, for instance, are cemented and then nailed in place.
The buildings look planted. It's a Victorian ode to the test of time.
So, let's find out how the best-built city in Britain copes with our pick-up truck.
Now, this, I want to make it plain, is not Hollywood.
We're not using stuntmen, we're not going to use any computer graphics.
We haven't made any mechanical alterations to the car at all.
We just picked it up from the farmyard and brought it here.
Oh, dearie me, that was a bit uncomfortable.
It damaged my spine quite badly doing this.
And then it set about...
...and then it set about...
...and then it set about damaging Bristol.
This didn't really hurt it either.
Yeah, battery's good, radiator's good.
That'll buff out.
That's got it.
So, we left the city centre and went to the seaside.
I'd tried careless driving...
...so I thought I'd try a spot of careless parking.
Look what's happened. This is the Severn Estuary,
home to the second biggest tide in the world.
40 feet, and it moves at eight miles an hour.
That's why the I and LI have tethered my car in place.
I'm not going to get that out for hours.
Damn!
The lifeboatmen and locals thought it was all a huge laugh.
-So, that's going to drown my car? -Oh, yes.
-When will I be able to get it out again? -To your ass.
Windscreen's still in.
But then, disaster.
The ropes tying it down had snapped.
It could be out in the main channel.
You may never see it ever again.
You don't think you've quite got this?
We've got to get it back.
Very kindly, they waded out to see if they could find it.
But it had gone.
And it didn't turn up until the tide had gone out five hours later.
The silt had jammed the steering lock,
and the cylinders were flooded with seawater.
The boat was now in a state of emergency.
The steering lock and the cylinders were flooded with seawater.
It was a wreck.
And though we'd brought a mechanic along, we had no spare parts.
Things looked bleak.
Well, the mechanic has worked on it now for 40 minutes or so, I think.
And it's not looking good.
Seems then that if you want to kill one of these things,
you have to reach the sea. Saltwater is the answer.
Sorry.
Erm, wrong.
Astonishingly, the Toyota was not dead.
I do not believe it!
Right, it's started.
Now, let's see if it moves.
(ALL CHEERING)
So, it had survived the West Country.
But would it survive our test track?
The problem is, what can we do here that we haven't already tried?
Difficult one.
I mean, the only solid structure we have here
is this, the Top Gear production office.
And that won't stop it.
The Americans have used daisy cutters on these things, to no avail.
But I've got something much more powerful.
The Mistral GT.
(GUNSHOTS)
What do you have to do to kill one?
Ah.
Right.
A bit undignified, but here we go.
Oh, lordy, lord. I'm too old for this.
(HORN HONKS)
I honestly can't believe this.
The steering's fine, the gearbox is fine, the low-range box is fine,
the brakes are fine.
Even the speedo's telling me we're doing 30.
To give you an idea of just how strong this car still is,
look what we've got here.
It's used to fell skyscrapers,
but look what happens when you thump it into the car.
Well, the day thou gavest, Lord, is ended.
But, sadly, the car isn't.
It survived trial by water,
it survived trial by Bristol and trial by caravan,
and the client must face the most difficult trial of them all.
Trial by fire.
(WHISTLES)
That was phenomenal.
- Amazing. - Be honest, did you really not change any bits?
Not a thing, other than the windscreen.
The sea took the windscreen out, we had to put a new one in
for driving through our production office,
otherwise it'd have taken my head off.
So we put a new piece of Perspex in, that was it.
Other than that, nothing. We just had hammers, spanners
and a bit of WD-40 to get the engine going after the sea.
All of which makes it more of a shame that, in the end, you killed it with fire.
- That was churlish. - Well, that's the thing.
You probably won't believe this, ladies and gentlemen.
I want a huge round of applause.
It is still working!
(CHEERING AND APPLAUSE)
Oh, my God!
My God!
Have you ever seen anything like it?
What have you done?
Oh, dear, it's not quite the same shape.
I think the tracking's out.
That was done when it was dropped.
You'll also notice, if you rock it slightly,
you can see, if we just bring the camera around here,
this headlamp has still got some of the Bristol Channel in it.
Oh, yes, and you've got a lighter on this corner as well.
- That was the tree. - That means it's an MOT failure.
- The bonnet did... - I'd like to do something about that.
The bonnet went up, but then the wrecking ball pushed it back down.
- The interior, not pretty. - Oh, no, you're right, that is...
- Yeah, it's a bit singed. - Yeah.
And I notice, above this enormous rust hole here,
there's quite a dent there as well.
That was the sum total of the damage from the caravan.
- And that little dent there... - What's in here?
That's your desk from the production office. You know you lost it.
- I used to sit there. - You did, that's bust.
This is quite interesting too. You see this little, er...
dent there? That was the wrecking ball.
That would knock down the Empire State Building. That's all it did.
And now we're going to talk about our pick-up truck.
You may remember we bought one a couple of weeks ago.
The idea was we were going to see if you could actually destroy it.
We tried drowning it in the Bristol Channel.
We smashed it through the Top Gear production office.
Dropped a caravan on it.
We hit it with one of those wrecking balls,
and then we set fire to it.
And it still survived.
Now, we concluded after that that it was pretty much unkillable.
Trouble is, though, you see, we were thinking laterally about this,
and what we needed to do was think vertically.
(DRUMMING)
This is Rachel Point Tower Block in Hackney, East London.
Former home to around 200 people,
23 storeys of late 1960s dream housing.
Well, in a few minutes, this monument to miserable Britain
will be reduced to a pile of rubble.
The building is meticulously laced with high explosives.
When they go off, this street in the sky will be brought down to earth with a bang.
Ah, you're thinking, "I bet they've parked the old Toyota right next to it."
But you'd be wrong, because we've come up with something much better.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC)
That's 240 feet up.
We're really not mucking about this time.
There are 12,500 tons of cancelled concrete in this building.
Nothing can possibly survive what is about to happen here.
-Do you think it'll survive? -No.
You never know what's going to happen. It could just disappear in with a pile.
Yeah, but what have you done? You've set fire to it, you've hit it with a wrecking ball,
you've put it in the sea. I think this will probably finish it off.
-It's not going to survive. -Do you want to bet?
-Yeah. -How much? -£10.
I'll have a tenner with you that you won't be able to drive out of.
-It's going to get expensive, isn't it? -It is.
Right, here we go.
Ten, nine, eight, seven, six, five, four, three, two, one.
(EXPLOSIONS)
(GUNFIRE)
So, the moment of truth. Will it be buried under thousands of tonnes of public housing?
No. There it is.
(GUNFIRE)
It may have escaped being buried alive, but that 240-foot drop has taken its toll.
It's smashed and bashed almost beyond recognition.
Oh, dear.
I'd say that was pretty ronnied. Have you got a crowbar with you?
Yep.
Again, we've got our mechanic with us, and as before, he's not allowed spare parts
and he can only use basic tools.
Too much. It doesn't look good.
-Right, is this it? -Right, this is it. I'm going to give it a go.
(MACHINE WHIRRING)
Come on.
(CHEERING)
Unbelievable.
But, but, but, but, but, but, but, OK, James.
James, now we've seen that it started.
-Yeah, it did start. -But did it move?
I can hardly believe this myself. Ladies and gentlemen, here it is!
(CHEERING)
It has come to life.
Yes! Yes!
(LAUGHTER)
Can I... I want to make sure... I want to make sure you're being honest, OK?
This is very important. When Jeremy did it, the rules were you couldn't replace any parts.
No spare parts allowed. You did the same. No spare parts.
No spare parts. The mechanic reconnected the battery, put a bit of diesel in it.
-Brum. Off it went. -I just can't believe it. I mean, look at the...
-The effect of that. -It's not bad. Taxed worse.
You've taxed worse. Oh, no, look here.
Look, the whole chassis is, well, I was going to say cracked, but split's a better word.
Yeah, well, it has actually broken in half right across,
and we're in the strange situation where the bodywork is actually holding the chassis.
(LAUGHTER)
I honestly... I'm stuck for... I mean, we could carry on trying to destroy it.
But do you know what? I think we should build a plinth. Yeah?
Put it on there as a museum piece for all of time. What do we think? Do we do that?
(CHEERING AND APPLAUSE)
(applause)